Well, as it turned out, the fantastic
prosperity of the 1920s came to an
inglorious end in 1929 when the economy
crashed harder than a generic stock
footage actor on the phone. So, that
means it's time to talk about the Great
Depression. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked limited welfare
state style, then let's get to it. Okay,
so let's start by getting everyone's
spirits up and talking about the causes
of that happy and carefree period in US
history known as the Great Depression.
But, before we launch into the causes,
let me remind you why the 1920s roared
so hard in the first place. Now, recall
what I said a couple of videos ago that
much of the economic flourishing of this
decade was owing to the continuing
transition from a rural agricultural
economy to an urban industrial economy
that focused more and more on the
production of consumer goods. And that
trend, chiefly spearheaded by several
large companies like Ford and Macy's
among many others, continued into the
1920s and contributed significantly to
the prosperity of this decade. And all
this to say the 1920s was a decade of
extraordinary prosperity for many,
though not all, Americans. And the
assumption was that the economy and the
associated boom boom would only continue
its rapid growth. But, on October 29th,
1929, that idealistic assumption was
hardly smacked from the American
consciousness on a day that became known
as Black Tuesday. On that day, the stock
market crashed, although to be fair, it
was kind of a week's-long process. But,
the United States was plunged into the
Great Depression, which would ultimately
last about a decade. And there are two
prominent causes for this economic
apocalypse that you're going to need to
stuff into your brain fold. But, before
I tell you what they are, let me throw
on some cheery music and tell you that
if you need help getting an A in your
class and a five on your exam in May,
you might want to check out my APUSH
Heimler review guide. This thing has
everything you need to get an A in your
class and a five on your exam in May,
and it's the fastest way to study. So,
if that's something that you're into,
check that link in the description.
Okay, so the first cause of the Great
Depression was the government's stubborn
unwillingness to assist farmers who had
been struggling financially. So, long
story short, farmers were one of the
main groups of Americans who, on the
whole, did not share in the economic
prosperity of the '20s. And why, says
you? Well, says I, a big reason is that
during World War I, farmers ramped up
production to meet wartime food needs.
But, after the war ended, farmers had
way more food than they had buyers. And
that overproduction meant that many
farmers were in debt and increasingly
unable to pay back their loans. And then
the second cause for the depression was
irresponsible stock trading prices that
virtually guaranteed an eventual crash.
You see, because the growth of the
market seemed unstoppable in the 1920s,
it became a common practice to allow
people to buy stocks on credit,
otherwise known as buying on margin. For
example, in some cases, people could buy
a share of a company for 5 to 10% of its
actual cost. And the assumption was that
since the market would continue to grow,
then eventually the value of the stock
would provide enough money to repay the
loan. But what happens when you borrow a
bunch of money that you don't have
stocks assuming that the value will
increase and then the bottom falls out.
Well, in addition to losing all the
value of your stock purchases, you're
also in crushing debt without the funds
to pay it back. And so, on Black
Tuesday, the artificial bubble that had
been inflated by all the speculative
stock purchases burst and then the value
of the stock market plummeted
dramatically. And in the immediate
aftermath, average Americans panicked
and rushed local banks in order to
withdraw their savings. But when the
banks couldn't sustain such withdrawals,
they began to fail rapidly and that
created even more ominous economic
conditions. And you're going to need to
know three effects of this economic
meltdown. First of all, this crisis
exposed the inefficacy of Republican
laissez-faire economic policies. So,
recall what I said in the previous video
that the 1920s was a decade marked by a
conservative reaction against the
liberalism of the progressive era. It
started with Warren G. Harding promising
a return to normalcy after all that
heavy government intervention from the
progressive. And a big slice of that
normalcy pie was a return to more
laissez-faire economic policies, which
is to say, let the market do its thing
unbothered by the government and
everybody's going to get rich. And that
policy continued through the
administration of Calvin Coolidge, who
presided over the height of the 1920s
prosperity. So, Republicans had a whole
lot of evidence that their economic
policies were doing exactly what they
said they would do, make America
wealthy. As long as you paid no
attention to farmers or black workers or
immigrants, but you know, otherwise
great. But then the Republican Herbert
Hoover entered office in March of 1929.
And remember, the stock market crashed
in October of that same year. So, in
March, Hoover is just riding the wave of
Republican prosperity and had no reason
to change his policies. But then, poor
guy, October comes around, the market
crashes and no small amount of chaos
ensues. So, Hoover was like conservative
policies gave us prosperity and
therefore conservative policies will end
the depression and give us back our
prosperity. And spoiler alert, that
strategy was about as effective as
trying to build a house with a hammer
made out of ham. I mean, sure it smells
nice and you have a nice convenient
snack anytime you want, but at the end
of the day, not the right tool for the
job. You see, Hoover believed, just like
the Republican presidents who preceded
him, that the solution to a crisis like
the Great Depression was the
intervention of private charities and
patently not the federal government.
That's because according to the economic
theory of Adam Smith, given enough time
the market will always correct itself.
And despite the fact that Hoover really
did seem to have genuine sympathy for
Americans suffering under the weight of
this disaster, Hoover essentially
allowed the depression to play out with
very little effort to counter its
effects. And apparently the scores of
Americans who had lost their homes due
to foreclosure weren't big fans of this
whole waiting for the market to correct
itself business. Many of them were
forced to take up residence in
shantytowns built from discarded trash
and detritus which they called
Hoovervilles just to let the president
know exactly what they thought about his
policies. And then the second effect of
the Great Depression was a larger global
economic failure. You see, after World
War I, several European economies relied
on American investment and loans in
order to rebuild after the war. And as
soon as the Great Depression hit, that
funding dried up quick, fast, and in a
hurry which led to further economic
collapse across Europe. And finally, the
third effect of the Great Depression was
that the US was ultimately transformed
into a limited welfare state. Now,
ultimately Hoover's policy of
non-interventionism proved exceedingly
unpopular with American voters and in
1932, he did not win a second term.
Instead, the Democrat Franklin Delano
Roosevelt won the election in a
landslide and Roosevelt was pretty much
Hoover's opposite when it came to
addressing the Great Depression because
Roosevelt was a big believer in
government intervention. And by
implementing his New Deal policies,
Roosevelt essentially transformed the US
into a limited welfare state by creating
social and economic safety nets for
Americans through a vigorous and
pervasive application of government
power. And as it happens, I'm going to
talk all about that New Deal in the next
video, so let's leave it there. Okay,
you can click here to watch my other
videos for unit 7 or you can click here
to grab my A Push Heimler Review Guide
which has everything you need to study
as fast as possible. I'm glad you came
around and I'll catch you on the flip
flop. Heimler out.